Approach Archives
Approach Archives
1913-1968
Approach magazine.
12 linear ft.
American literary journal. Collection contains editorial files, correspondence with authors and contributors, copies of other "little magazines," indexes to APPROACH, more. List of names given in subject headings below is not comprehensive.
3283018
Biographical History
APPROACH was an American literary magazine that flourished between 1947 and 1962. It published both prose and poetry, and counted among its authors Robert Bly, Charles Bukowski, Daniel Hoffman, Lachlan MacDonald, Thomas Merton, Howard Nemerov, and many more.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The APPROACH Archives contains editorial files, books, magazines and miscellaneous material. The donor's original organization has been retained. This Scope and Content section has been written by, but all folder titles and descriptions in the "Inventory" section below are taken directly from the donor's extensive and detailed finding aid.
APPROACH files contains issue files, correspondence and miscellany. Issue files consists of one file for each of the 64 issues of the magazine; each file may contain a wide range of material including letters from authors, permissions, copyright information, financial material, drafts of prose or poems, receipts, notices, precis, reports, subscriber names and addresses, and so on. Correspondence is subdivided into correspondence with contributing authors and correspondence with others (would-be contributors, readers, the general public). Miscellaneous files at the end of this series include advertising rates, unfinished articles, inventories, lists of nominees for prizes, circulars and rejections from other magazines, correspondence with bookstores and libraries, policies, submissions, and assorted other material.
Books consists of -- to use Approach's own words -- "Published works of our contributors, plus those books judged important for understanding the period from 1947-1967." The first section consists of prose and poetry by authors including Robert Bly, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Albert Fowler and Thomas Merton, among others. The second section consists of references works such as "indices, bound volumes of out-of-print little magazines of the preceding generation, histories of little magazines, general works of reference and anthologies." Two vanity press items complete this series.
Magazines consists of issues of publications with which Approach had an exchange agreeement, and a selection of publications which wished to exchange with Approach but which Approach rejected. Most of the former have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging and may be located via. The latter range from college English publications and University press organs to publications from correctional institutions and religious organizations; most are American but there are also a few from Britain, Canada and Spain.
Miscellaneous items consists of back issues and reprints of issues of Approach, indexes to the publication, three books of expenses and receipts, and notebooks of subscriber names and addresses. There are also three copies of Berdyaev "On Suicide."
Arrangement of the Collection
The APPROACH files retain the original organization, structure and file names as received. Issue files are in chronological order by issue number. Correspondence is in alphabetical order by correspondent name. Books are in alphabetical order by author while magazines are in alphabetical order by title. Miscellaneous items are in no particular order.
Separated Material
Many of the books, serials, journals and periodicals that comprised the original donation have been transferred to Rare Books or to the circulating collection for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Publishing, printing and book arts; Radicalism; Aiken, Conrad, 1889-1973.; Bly, Robert.; Bukowski, Charles.; Brooks, Helen Morgan.; Carruth, Hayden, 1921-2008.; Everson, William, 1912-1994.; Fowler, Albert Vann, 1904-; Foley, Helen.; Kreymborg, Alfred, 1883-1966.; Landstrom, Elsie H.; Lewis, C. S. (Clive Staples), 1898-1963.; MacDonald, Lachlan P.; McCandless, John H.; McDonald, Frank.; Merton, Thomas, 1915-1968.; Murphy, Carol R.; Nemerov, Howard.; O'Connor, Flannery.; Savory, Teo.; Swallow, Alan, 1915-1966.; Approach.; American literature -- 20th century -- Periodicals.; American poetry -- 20th century -- Periodicals.; American literature -- History and criticism -- Periodicals.; Literature, Modern -- 20th century -- Periodicals.; Poetry, Modern -- 20th century -- Periodicals.; Advertisements.; Contracts.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Magazines (periodicals); Manuscripts for publication.; Reviews (documents)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Albert and Helen Fowler, 1968.
Inventory
- APPROACH files
  - Issues files
    - #1, Spring, 1947 (Box 1)
      containing letters from Frank T. Prince, James Agee, Kenneth Patchen, William Eshelman, and the Hambleton Company of Wilmington, Del., printers
    - #2, Summer, 1947 (Box 1)
      containing a letter from Hubert Creekmore of New Directions, from the Hambleton Co., financial reports on the first 2 issues
    - #3, Fall, 1947 (Box 1)
      containing letters about copyright, about permission for the translation of Ricarda Huch's "Verses for our Time," from Lloyd Sullivan, and Libertarian Print Shop of Newark, N.J.
    - #4, Spring, 1948 (Box 1)
      containing letters from Kenneth Rexroth, Anne Freund, Elsie Hines (Landstrom) the Copyright Office, and Libertarian Print Shop
    - #5, Spring, 1949 (Box 1)
      containing letters from Marie Rexroth, Kenneth Patchen, James Laughlin, Edwin A. Sanders, the Printing Department. of William Penn College, Oskaloosa, Iowa, and financial accounting
    - #6, Spring, 1950 (Box 1)
      containing permissions from Houghton Mifflin 0o. for certain lines from Archibald MacLeish's "Poems, 1924-1933" and New Directions for permission to quote from Ezra Pound's "The Seafarer" in Personae, letters from John H. McCandless who he'd-set and printed the issue at Black Mountain College, Black Mountain, N.C. and Frank McDonald, APPROACH editor, financial reports, a copy of the first, APPROACH advertising in Mason Jordan Mason's Notebook 4-23. Also permission request from William Hull for "Song Some Scientists Don't Sing"
    - #7, Spring, 1952 (Box 1)
      containing a copy of the speech given by Albert Fowler on the 5th birthday party of APPROACH given at Pendle Hill, Wallingford, Pa. on May 25, the first & second drafts of J.H. McCandless' poem read on the same occasion, "Milton, Thou Shouldest Be Living at This Hour, or One of Our Editors is Missing; greetings from Howard Brinton, APPROACH newsletters by Frank McDonald, J.H. McCandless, letter from James S Holmes written from Holland, 14'.17ine(r or people sending in contributions, financial report, and inventory, no letters from Roberts of Media, Pa. who did the printing for this issue since Frank McDonald was business agent and did not turn over to us later, this correspondence
    - #8, Spring, 1953 (Box 1)
      reports from Frank McDonald, Albert Fowler, Peter Docili, J.H. McCandless, Elsie Hines (Landstrom); a letter from Libertarian Press which did not handle the printing (Suburban Publications of Wayne, Pa. did the printing but there are no records of receipts); financial reports, notices about APPROACH in Friends Intelligencer, Pendle Hill Bulletin, Quaker Wider Fellowship, and letters from Olive Johnson, Vincent Kanes, Lesley West, and John L. Heller
    - #9, Fall, 1953 (Box 1)
      proposal to change APPROACH to a quarterly basis, letters from editors, McDonald, Landstrom, Murphy, Docili approving the change of address and timing, cover proof, treasurer's report, report on subscriptions, reports from readers, letters from Richard Kirk Washburn, Norman Whitney, Ruth Forbes Sherry, John L. Heller, Kenneth Burke, Katherine Bragdon, poem by Albert Fowler, contributors' addresses
    - #10, Winter, 1954 (Box 1)
      letter from F. McDonald, from Charles Scribner's Sons, printing receipt from Suburban Publications, precis for Contributors' Notes from Milton Gordon, Elsie Landstrom, Frona Lane, Glen Coffield, Mildred Murphy, Olive Johnson, William Hull, LeGarde S. Doughty, letters from Richard Kirk Washburn, Anne G. Sneller, APPROACH ad in The Creative Advertiser, editor: Glen Coffield, Vol I, No. 1, Spring 1954, Contributors' addresses
    - #11, Spring, 1954 (Box 1)
      report from H. Fowler, vita from Vincent Oredson, and Dachine Rainer, letters from Olive Johnson, Richard Kirk Washburn, Margaret Kirkpatrick, Elsie Landstrom, Trace No 8, Aug. 1954 descriptive of the issue, Suburban Publications receipt, contributors' addresses
    - #12, Summer, 1954 (Box 1)
      letters from Glen Coffield, LeGarde S. Doughty, Richard Kirk Washburn, R.S. Fetters, Frona Lane - asking for permission to tape record poems of Ethelford Carroll, Suburban Publications receipts, contributors' addresses
    - #13, Fall, 1954 (Box 1)
      A. Fowler's treasurer's report, list of contributors' & exchange copies, request. from Kenneth R. Jones of Salem County Farmers Almanac to reprint Mary Hoxie Jones' "Man and Child," M.H. Jones' permission, copy of the Almanac for Jan. 1954, letters from Frederick F. Manfred, Ruth Domino, and Borestone Mountain Awards' inquiry into APPROACH's status, APPROACH's nominations for 8th annual contest, Suburban Publications' receipts, contributors' addresses
    - #14, Winter, 1955 (Box 1)
      A. Fowler's financial report, letters to and from the copyright office concerning the lost certificate No. B 522716, date Feb. 20, 1955, vitas from Charles Edward Eaton, Theodore Enslin, George H. Moorse, letters from Norman Whitney, Margaret Kirkpatrick, Chet Bryant, Peter Docili, and Theodore Enslin, from George Knox re an article on Kenneth Burke which did not materialize, Suburban Publications' receipt, contributors' addresses
    - #15, Spring, 1955 (Box 1)
      reports on make-up from H. Fowler & finances from A. Fowler, letter from copyright office concerning printer's error in dropping copyright notice on title page after approval of page proofs, and a copy of the law, vita of Barron Mills, letters from Margaret Kirkpatrick, Roy Livengood, and Norman Whitney, listing of copies & contributors' addresses
    - #16, Summer, 1955 (Box 1)
      A. Fowler's financial report, letters from and to F. McDonald, vita from Charlotte Marletto, letter from Marion Kingston of Beloit Poetry Journal re Carroll Arnett, Suburban Publications' receipts and Contributors' addresses
    - #17, Fall, 1955 (Box 1)
      letters to and from John V. Sankey of Villiers Publications, London, England & James Boyer May and receipted bills from the same, copy of U.S. Law implementing the Universal copyright Convention & a letter from U.S. Copyright Office, vitas from Don Geiger & Emory C. Pharr, letters from Richard L. Barrows, Jr. and Elizabeth Schneider, note from William Newberry, clipping from Intro Bulletin-Jan, 1956, Albert Fowler's financial report, contributors' addresses
    - #18, Winter, 1956 (Box 1)
      letters to and from John Sankey, receipted bills, letter from David Hudson requesting permission to reprint Helen Morgan Brooks "Three Poems," "The Sere, The Yellow Leaf," "Letter to Sheila," letters to and from James S Holmes who assumed proofing and paging from his home in Amsterdam, Holland, vita of Holmes, clipped from The Friends Intelligencer, early Feb., 1956, part of a letter from Addison Allen, contributors' addresses
    - #19, Spring, 1956 (Box 1)
      first draft of Albert Fowler's "Poor Man's Saturday Reviews," first draft of Wolf Mendi's "Angle of a Screen," note about first copies to writers' conferences, letters to and from John Sankey, James S. Holmes, and James Boyer May, printing receipts, notation about shipment, card from Bernard Raymund, Albert Fowler's financial reports, contributors' addresses
    - #20, Summer, 1956 (Box 1)
      first draft of Harold Grutzmacher's "The Clearing," carbons of title page and Contributors' Notes, letters to and from Sankey, Holmes, May, and printing receipts, routing of copy for the issue among the editors, notes for editorial meeting 4/15/56, letters to Collector of Customs, Philadelphia, receipt for duty paid, letter from U.S. Treasury, Customs Service, about what to do to avoid duties, contributors' addresses
    - #21, Fall, 1956 (Box 1)
      minutes for editorial meeting 8/26/56, copy of Opal Shannon's letter to The Golden Goose, requesting return of the mss "O, That Is This to me ...", letters to and from Holmes, Sankey's delivery note, printing receipts, note about Helen Fowler's publicity letters, copy of Albert Fowler's "Meridian at Midcentury," letters from Norman Whitney, Ruth Smith and Richard Barrows, contributors' addresses
    - #27, Winter, 1957 (Box 1)
      Helen Fowler's editorial queries about Arnett's article on William Jay Smith, carbons of contributors' notes & title page, letters to and from Farrar, Straus & Young about permission to quote from Smith's poems, letters to and from Arnett over what to do because we refused to pay the charges, letters to and from Sankey, Holmes and May, printing receipts, H. Fowler's minutes for editorial meeting, letter from Olive Johnson and Frederick Bock, clipping from N.Y. Times book review, Mar. 24, 1957, reprinting Alan Donovan's "Of Bones and Stars," contributors' addresses
    - #23, Spring, 1957 (Box 1)
      letter from Wolf Mendl, Albert Fowler's financial reports, carbon of title page, make up of cover for 10th Anniversary issue, letters to and from Sankey, Holmes & May, authorization for business reply cards, printing receipts, record of shipment, notes about complimentary copies and publicity letters, letter from J.H. McCandless, note on gift of mailing envelopes, contributors' addresses
    - #24, Summer, 1957 (Box 1)
      carbons of title page & contributors' notes, letters to Sankey, Holmes, letters from Holmes & May, printing receipts & shipment records, N.Y. Times Book Review for July 21, 1957 containing reprint of Gerhard Friedrich's "Four-Thirty by the Clock" and contributors' addresses
    - #25, Fall, 1957 (Box 1)
      carbon of contributors' notes, letters from & to Sankey, letters to Holmes, printing receipts, shipment record, letter from Irving Leiberman of Cleveland Writers' conference re cost of names of participants on gummed labels, labels, contributors' addresses, letter from Elined Kotschnig
    - #26, [Winter 1958?] (Box 1)
      Contributors' notes, make-up, letters to and from May & Holmes, letters to Sankey, printing receipts, invoice, letter from Miriam T. Ellison of Best Articles & Stories, requests from same for permissions to reprint Robert Sward's "By the Swimming," and Philip Appleman's "Muses des Beaux Arts," copies of permissions granted Sward for said poem and Lee Brown Coye for "The Way to Go Home," contributors' addresses and Appleman's request
    - #27, Spring, 1958 (Box 1)
      letters to and from Sankey & Holmes, letters from May, printing receipts & invoice, note from Philip Appelman, and Ray Smith, permission requests from BA&S for J.H. McCandless' "Salute to an Honest Confectioner," Margaret Tongue's "April's Child," and permissions request from Robert L. Tyler for his "First Person," contributors' addresses and carbon of contributors' notes
    - #28, Summer, 1958 (Box 1)
      make-up for contributors' notes, letters to Sankey & Holmes, letters from Sankey & May, printing receipts & invoice, letter from Waddell Austin asking permission to reprint Joseph Tanda's "Cum Laude" in Borestone Mountain's 11th annual anthology, permission for Barriss Mills' "Everybody Cried at Our Wedding" in BA&S, contributors' addresses
    - #29, [Fall 1958?] (Box 1)
      Helen Fowler's notes of 1/10/68 explaining background for the following letters from Sarah A. Haigler, David Lyttle, Howard Comfort, Eugene Exman, F. Edward Lund, Tom F. Driver, Edith Warren Johnson, letter to Holmes, letter from Sankey, page make-up, letters to and from J. H. McCandless who took over the printing of the magazine for the rest of its life, receipts for carting & printing, note on typographical errors in Albert Fowler's "The Rebels Against Man's Condition," part of a letter from Anne G. Sneller, contributors' addresses
    - #30, Winter, 1959 (Box 1)
      carbons for a flyer and title page, letters to and from J.H. McCandless, letters to Holmes and an editorial minute letter to absentee editors Landstrom, McDonald & McCandless, printing receipts, copy of change in the notice provisions of US copyright law, permission requests from BA&S for Marie Chay's "We're All the Same Now" and Joseph Joel Keith's "The Pen," request from James L. Weil of The Elizabeth Press for permission for Keith poem, copy of permissions granted Keith for "The Pen," LAND OF MORNING, IN A FAR COUNTRY, THE IDOL, contributors' addresses
    - #31, Spring, 1959 (Box 1)
      letters to and from J.H. McCandless, carbons of cover, salute to Hemlock Press, title page, contributors, features of #32, proofs of title page, J.H.M's poem "No" and Pasternak translation (1) and APPROACHing, printing receipts, letter from Donna Collins, coordinator of Views receipt of payment for ad in the London Times Literary Supplement, letters from Miriam T. Ellison requesting permissions for George Garrett's "The Only Dragon on the Road," the two Pasternak poems "The Drowsy Garden" and "Resting Oars" translated by Kayden, and Peter Crumpet's "Roll Over Poets," permission request from University of Massachusetts for David R. Clark's "The Promise," letter from Willis Eberman about mention of his book THE PIONEERS AND OTHER POEMS, break-down of distribution, contributors' addresses
    - #32, Summer, 1959 (Box 1)
      letters to and from JHM, carbons of cover, recent comments about APPROACH, title page, contributors, APPROACHing, printing receipts, letters from A. Fowler, trying to elicit comments from Eugene Exman & Tillich on C.S. Lewis, letter from William Hubben, editor of Friends Journal, letters and permission request from BA&S for Albert Fowler's "The Lost Relevance of Religion," copy of application for registration of a claim to copyright, letters from Den Wilson, Anne G. Sneller, and Josephine Benton, contributors' addresses
    - #33, Fall, 1959 (Box 1)
      letters to and from JHM, carbons of cover, title page, contributors, APPROACHing, reprint cover for John Nist's "Brasil is Awake," note for Albert Fowler's poem, "Loon Lake," H. Fowler's tentative paging, and letter from Bradley on make-up, letter from Marion Stocking of THE BELOIT POETRY JOURNAL releasing copyright on Nist's translation of Bandeira's "Profundamente," printing receipts, letter from Margaret Widdem of Huntington Hartford Foundation, contributors' addresses
    - #34, Winter, 1960 (Box 1)
      letters to and from JHM, carbons of cover, title page, contributors, APPROACHing, printing receipts, contributors addresses
    - #35, Spring, 1960 (Box 1)
      letters to and from JHM, carbons of cover, notes for inside front cover on Lyttle's & McAfee's books, and note on purpose of Notes and Cross References to Nature, a subdivision on title page, title page, contributors, APPROACHing, proofs of covers, printing receipts, permission request from BA&S for Carroll Arnett's "The Question," copyright transfers to Ann Stanford of "Small Garden," "The Protestant," "The Sleeping Princess," contributors' addresses
    - #36, Summer, 1960 (Box 1)
      letters to and from JHM and Sam Bradley who had the management of this issue about the 7 APPROACH poets, carbons of flyer, cover, title page and contributors, letters to SB about the issue from P. J. Kaufman (Critical Quarterly) Theodore Weiss, Robert Lescher (Henry Halt) Arthur R. Borden, Jr. (Shenandoah) John Hall Wheelock, Richard Kelly (Half Moon) Evelyn Thorne, Dick Evans, Reed Whittemore, August Derleth, Joli Morgan for John Logan (Choice) about mention of this forthcoming magazine and the Poetry Contest of Poetry Seminar, Chicago, .permissions for Charles Black's "Aspects" and "Old Woman Serving Behind a Counter," lists of writers to be informed about APPROACH's plans, printing receipts, contributors' addresses
    - #37, Fall, 1960 (Box 1)
      letters to and from JHM, carbons of insert, cover, title page and contributors, printing receipts, permission requests from BA&S for JH. McCandless' "How I Became an American Citizen," and Bernice Ames' "Under a Banner," copyright transfer to Charles Philbrick for "The Presence Upstairs," contributors' addresses
    - #38, Winter, 1961 (Box 1)
      letters to and from JHM, carbons of cover, notes on retirement of Frank McDonald & Elsie Landstrom as editors and the McCandless' lawsuit (not used) title page, contributors' notes, APPROACHing, requests for back copies for libraries, some page proofs, N.Y. Herald Tribune of Feb. 26, 1961 reprint of Lloyd Frankenberg's "A Case of Identity," permission from University of Detroit Press to quote from Brother Antoninus' THE CROOKED LINES OF GOD, permission from Grove Press for Michael Hamburger's translations, permissions from Charles Philbrick & Wake Brook House for quotes from WONDERSTRAND REVISITED, permissions request from Charles Scribner's for Peter Viereck's "The Aunt Creed," which was our title, permission to Bink Noll for "Wallace Stevens," to William Jay Smith for "Bachelor's Buttons" & "Dachshunds," printing receipts, contributor's addresses
    - #39, Spring, 1961 (Box 1)
      letters to and from JHM, notes from editorial meeting (early spring, 1961, undated), carbon of Foreword to The Fish God, original drawings, page proofs of drawings, carbon of Index #34 to 38, and cumulative index up to and including #39, page proofs of both, copy of printed cumulative index and Fish God flyer, printing receipts
    - #40, Summer 1961 (Box 1)
      letters to and from JHM, letters to Grove Press asking permission to quote from John Muir's COLLECTED POEMS, to the Hogarth Press re: Muir's AN AUTOBIOGRAPHY, to Encounter, Robert Fitzgerald & Bollingen for permissions to use the translation in part of John Perse's "Chronique," to POETRY for John Ciardi's "Divorced Husband Demolishes House," to Scribner's for Paris Leary's Views of the Oxford Colleges and Other Poems, letters to and from Edwin Geauque of Wake Brook House re a full page ad in APPROACH for Sister Mary Honora's, Charles Philbrick's and Edna Meudt's books, letters from John Berry and his agent about our permission for "The Pious Puzzles," permissions granted to Elizabeth Randall-Mills for "Every Sleeper Loved," Donald Baker for "Penelope Weaving" & "Biography," printing receipts, distribution note, contributors' addresses
    - #41, Fall, 1961 (Box 1)
      letters to and from JHM, H. Fowler's report to editors, carbons for cover, title page, contributors' notes, letter from Sam Bradley about Kayden's refusal of honorary degree for his translations of Pasternak and carbon of note on same, Sam Bradley's Note on Alexander Tvardovsky and carbon of cut copy, note on make-up of insertion and carbon of insertion, note on distribution, proofs of ads in The Nation, copy of second class postage, contributors' addresses
    - #42, Winter, 1962 (Box 1)